First of all, let me say that I am delighted to be back home at Harvard.
I'm also somewhat petrified at the grandeur of the poetic chair I am occupying;
a chair which has over the years grown into soemthing more like a throne,
owing to the long list of eminent persons who have occupied it.
It's a tough act to follow, but I am comforted by the sense of having come home again,
and happy to be realizing my old student fantacy of what it's like to be on the other side of the desk.
Now that I AM on the side of the desk, all I seem to be able to think about is how it felt to be on THAT side,
Felt good -- if you want to know the truth -- those thirty years ago.
Maybe because I was very lucky in my masters:
Piston and Merit in Music; Patridge and Spenser in Literature;
Demoson and Hocking in Philosophy.
But there was one master who bridge it all for me.
Through whom the sense of beauty, analytic method, and historical perspective,
all came together in one luminous revelation.
And I would like to dedicate this six lectures to his memory.
He was professor David Prall of the philosophy department
-- a brilliant scholar and a deeply sensitive aesthitician.
It was in this now disdained and rather unfashionable field of aesthetics,
that I learned from him not only a great deal about the philosophy of beauty,
but also the fact that David Prall was himself an instance of the beauty he loved,
in mind, heart and spirit.
Those are terribly old-fastioned words in these days of behaviouristic of obsessiveness,
and I hope you will pardon such ancient words as mind, heart and spirit specially since I believe them as strongly now as I did then.
Perhaps the principle thing I absorbed from professor Prall and from Harvard in general,
was the inter-disciplinary spirit, that the best way to know a thing is in a context of another discipline.
So these lectures are given in that spirit of cross disciplines which is why
I'll be speaking of music along with quixotic forays into such fields as poetry,
linguistics, aesthetics and -- even heaven help us -- a bit elementary physics.
The title of this lecture series is borrowed from Charlse Ives
who wrote that brief but remarkable piece of his called "The Unanswered Questions" way back in 1908.
Ives had a highly metaphysical question in mind,
but I've always felt he was also asking another question, a highly a purely musical one:
whither music, as that question must have been asked by musical man entering the 20th century,
today with that century 65 years older, we are still asking it.
Only it is not quite the same question as it was then, and so the purpose of these six lectures is not so much to answer the question as to understand it,
to redefine it, even to guess at the answer to whither music, we must first ask whence(?) music, what music, whose music.
It will be pretentious to assume that by the end of the series we will answer the ultimate question,
but it's reasonable to assume that we'll be at a better position to make some educated guesses.
Let me start with a particularly nostalgic and vivid recollection from my years with professor Prall.
The time back in 1937, when I first heard a recording of Alvin Coplin's piano variations,
I fell in love with the music. It seemed so fiece and poetic, and utterly new.
This music opened up new worlds of musical possibilities to me,
and I wrote a raving report on it for my aesthetics course,
and Professor Prall became so interested in it that he decided he wanted to learn it himself.
What a man, even bought me the sheet music!
So I learned it and taught it to him and he taught it back to me, and we analysed it together, and it became our song.
This is now just a sentimental anecdote, because as we were analysing the Colplin variations I made a startling discovery,
that the first four notes of the piece,
which are the germ of the whole composition, are really these four notes,
with the fourth note at an octive higher.
And I suddenly perceived that the same four notes in another order
form the subject of Bach's C sharp minor fugue, from the well tempered clavier chord
And then I discovered that the same four notes transposed, with the first note repeated,
germinating the variations in Stravinsky's Octet.
And the same four notes then popped up yet in another order and key as the initial motto of Ravel's Spanish Rhapsody.
And on top of all that I suddenly recalled some Hindu music I had heard -- I was a big oriental music buff at the time,
and there woo the same four notes again.
And at that moment, a notion was born in my brain
that there must be some deep primal reason why these discrete structures of the same four notes
should be at the very heart of such disparate musics as those of Bach, Colplin, Stravinsky, Ravel and the UdeShanka(?) dance company.
And all this, and more, I poured out to David Prall, and that was my first Norton lecture to an audience of one.
And from that time to this, the notion of a worldwide inborn musical grammar has haunted me.
But I will never have dreamed of basic lectures series on a notion so ill-defined and apparantly non-verifiable,
if it were not for the extraordinary materials that have appeared in recent years on the similar idea of a universal grammar underline human speech.
I've been profoundly impreesed and encouraged by the burgeoning of thought in this relatively new linguistic area;
an area that might be called Chomtskian.
By so name it I don't mean to restrict my observations to known Chomtsky's work alone.
It's a term of convenience, since he is the best known, most revolutionary and best publicised name in that area.
Along his collegues and disciples, many of whom are now in radical disagreement with him,
he has produced a body of work that has re-invagorated linguistics to a point where it seems new light may be shed
on the nature and structural functions of that elusive thing called Mind.
In other words, by studying in depth why we talk the way we do, by abstracting the logic principles of language,
we maybe at a position to discover how we can communicate in a larger sense through music, through the arts in general,
and ultimately through all our societal behaviour.
We may even discover how we are mentally constituted because language is species-specific,
that is it's common to all of us who belong to the human species and only to us.
Of course tomorrow morning cheerful new facts about dolphins
or certain chimpanzee named Zira may throw a monkey wrench to the works,
but meanwhile this philosophical science called linguistics
seems to have become our newest key to self discovery; with each passing year seems to substanciate ever more convincingly
the hypothesis of the innate grammatical competence as Chomtsky calls it,
genetically endowed language faculty which is universal;
it's a human endowment; it proclaims the autonomy of the human spirit.
Well, so does music. But how do we investigate musical universality by so scientific a means as linguistic analogy?
Music is supposed to be a metaphorical phenomenon, some kind of mysterious symbolisation of our inner most affective existence.
It lends itself more easily to descriptions in purple prose than in equations.
And even so great a scientist as Einstein said that the most beautiful experience we can have is the mysterious
-- of course he played the fiddle and he loved music.
But then why do some many of us constantly try to explain the beauty of music?
That's apparently depriving it of it's own mystery.
The fact is that music is not only a mysterious and metaphorical art, it is also in itself a science;
it's made of mathmatically measurable elements: frequencies, durations, decibels, intervals.
So any explication of music must combine mathematics with aesthetics just as linguistics combine mathematics with philosophy, or sociology, or whatever.
It is precisely for this inter-disciplinary reason that I'm so attracted by the new linguistics as a fresh approach to music,
(quite not)??? as the study of musical linguistics, just as there already exist as a psyco-linguistics, and a socio-linguistics.
Alright, let's try it. Luckily the study of linguistics is a three fold science and so provides us with three handy categories in which these lectures can be conceived.
One phonology, two syntax, and three semantics.
Phonology, syntax, semantics, these are three departments of linguistics and they point the way for our musical investigations as well.
In this first lecture, we will oriented phonologically, examining both language and music from a most fundamental point of view that of sound itself;
the stuff of which verbal and musical utterences are made.
And that should give us a solid base to build on, so that in our next session we can plunge into syntax,
the actual structures that arise from that phonologic stuff.
From then on, the remaining four lectures will confront the challenges of semantics, that is meaning, both musical and extra-musical meaning.
Semantics can be seen as the natural result of adding phonology and syntax together: sound plus structure.
And the resultant semantic enquiry will bring us around back to Ives unanswered question whither music in our time.
And now you can see why I became so excited when I began reading the new linguistics,
which postulated the notion of innate linguistic competence, because suddenly my old under-graduated notion of a universal muscial grammar was re-animated.
It lay dormant for years, paralysed, I suppose, by that deadly cliche: Music is the universal language of mankind.
After a thousand repetitions of that one, usually with the connotation support your local symphony orchestra,
the well-meant phase becomes not only a cliche, but a misleading one.
How many of you can listen to forty minutes of a Hindu Raga with intelligent comprehension,
to say nothing of merely saying awake.
And how about certain kinds of avant-garde music: not so universal, are they?
Well, thought I so much for the universal language of mankind.
But then when I began reading the new lingustics, I thought here is a fresh way to pursue my intuitive idea,
which had grown still and deteriorated into a platitude.
In other words, by building analogies between muscial and linguistc procedures,
couldn't that cliche of that universal language be debunked? Or confirmed? Or at least clarified?
OK, let's clarify. Universality is a big word and a dangerous one.
At the same time that it implies likeness as it also implies diversity.
Remember Montaigne's remark that "the most universal quality of man is his diversity".
This paradox lies at the very heart of linguistics study
because at the same time that a linguist is investigating any one particular language or even a family of languages,
trying to formulate a descriptive grammar,
is also searching for the underlying similarities among different languages or families of languages.
At least the new linguists are.
They construct these descriptive grammars by analysing the mental processes of human speech,
that's deriving sets of rules that hopefully apply to all human languages,
in fact to all possible human languages, both known and unknown.
Now that's a tall order, but a magnificent goal requiring an inspiring guess of the great scientific leap of the mind.
And if that goal can be attained and the universality principle proved, it can turn out to be a timely and welcome affirmation of human brotherhood.
But how do linguists go about such a task? Well, one way is by seeking out what they call substantive universals.
For example, in the realm of phonology, which is our main concern in this lecture,
linguists propose a substantive universal which says the following: all languages share certain phonemes in common,
that is minimal speech units that arise natually from the physiological structure of our mouths, throats and noses.
Since we all share those features we share likewise the sound "A" for instance,
a sound produced by simply opening the mouth and vocolising it -- "A".
Every normal human being can do this in any language, there is simply no exception,
even though the vowel may vary according to the shape of the oral cavity, or according to one's social background,
producing such variance as "cla:ss" and "class" and "claess".
But they are all versions of the same phoneme "A", and so must be considered universal.
Now that's a substantive universal voile.
Other linguists, of course I'm skipping enormous numbers of other substantive universals and distinctive features, I don't want to burden you with all that,
but other, certain other linguists go about seeking universals in different ways, such as etymologists,
who point out that the interesting thing about the Spainsh word "allad", to speak, and the Portuguese equivalent "fallad", to speak,
is not that they seem to be totally different words, but that they are the same word deriving from the same Latin root "fabolale",
but with phonetic deviations.
Let's not go into why they are deviated, though it's a facinating subject. Let's agree only about the common origin.
There's the key, common origin.
Because one continues in this way, working backwards through history in search of even ealier common origins,
one arrives at startling points of universality, only such investigation has to stop short as soon as written languages run out.
Because obviously the ultimate evidence of universality in speech is to be sought in the oldest languages of Man,
pre-historical languages which preceded, so to speak, the Tower of Babel moment in human evolution.
But such ancient languages simply don't exist.
They were spoken millions of years ago, long before written languages be developed, which was only thousands of years ago.
And so being stuck with out-written evidence, historical linguists are forced into speculation.
Ideally, what they are seeking is a parent language, one universal tongue that may have been common to all of early mankind.
And that's the tallest order of all, because it means wandering in the mists of pre-history.
One tangible accomplishment at least has been to find a name for this field of enquiry,
and that name is "monogenesis", denoting the theory of all languages bringing from a single source.
A fine word, monogenesis, and a thilling idea.
It thrills me anyway to the point where I stayed up all of one night, making monogenetic speculations of my own.
I tried to imagine myself a hominid, and tried to feel what a very very ancient ancestor of mine
might have felt and might have been impelled to express verbally.
I scribbled pages full of basic mono-syllables which felt somehow right, which seem to belong together,
and which delighted me with their curious logic. I began by imagining myself a homonid infant,
just lying there contentedly trying out my new-found voice. Um...
Then I got hungary, Um..! Calling my mother's attentions to my hunger. And as I opened my mouth to receive the nipple,
Um..Ah! Know I've invented my primal word -- Ma, mother.
This is got to be one of the first proto words ever uttered by Man.
Still to this day, most languages have a word for mother that employs that root -- "Ma", or some phonetic variant for it.
All the Romance languages... so on the Germanic.... Slavic... Hebrew ... Navajo, even Navajo, even Swahili
and Japanese and Chinese, they call her Mama.
Well, that was a small triumph. And then I began expanding.
What about "Ma" plus "L"? Say, "mal". Well, now there's a proto syllable for you.
My first association, of course, was with all the familiar words connoting badness: "malo", "male", "molve".
All Latin derived languages, of course; then I thought, in the Slavic family of languages, that syllable connotes smallness:
"malle", "malo", "malinky" and so on.
Sudden hypothesis: could there just possibly be a monogenetic connection way back then between the concepts of badness and smallness.
Why not? Remember we are being harmonids now and it's perfectly conceivable that what small must be automatically bad.
To be small is to be weak, to be only human, as against the powerful gods; as against the huge magical earth and sky.
Hence weaknesses undesirable, hence bad. It's bad to have small harvest, small images, small stature, small dinner, "malo".
Then I thought, if that's true, then big must equal good; there must be a corresponding kinship between bigness and goodness.
So when I went searching through all the dictionaries I can find, what do you think? I found it.
Most familiar root denoting bigness is "er" -- the growling of the big tiger, produce all the big words: grandy, grandir, grace, grow and even including () in Dutch
where g is soften to the gutteral ().
And all these are in Latin and Germanic, but again look at the Slavic, where again the "g" is gutteralised to "h"
And behold the glorious word (), which means so inevitably and comfortingly good.
And () is brave and big brave good and God.
Somehow it all adds up. Way back before and behind and beyond all these comparatively recent languages,
there must lurk, I fondly hoped, one universal pararnt tongue, which contains the great simultaneous equation:
big equals good and small equals bad. Triumph!
By why am I burdening your with my private game playing? This less than scientific speculation, it's hardly what a liguist will call authentic.
I cannot say strongly enough that I claim the right to be wrong. It's every teacher's academic right, and I stand ready to take the risk involved,
just as any theorist or scientist does.
So my monogenetic speculation interests me and I hope you because of what it suggests about music.
The origins of music and the very nature of musical materials, the notes themselves.
Let's make a simple analogy and return for a second to being that harmonid infant who invent that proto word - "ma"
And we quickly learn to associate that morpheme with our supplier of milk, right?
So we call her when we need her -- "ma".
Now on a pure phonological level, that begins at sound, begins with an attack, an ictus.
"ma" and ends in a descending glide.
"ma" that's the way we speak, ictus plus glide.
Of course the glide may also be upward if the intention is interogative -- "ma".
Now let's feel a tremendous intensification of our need, of our hunger, of our patience,
so we intensify the ictus by prolonging it -- "ma--"
And lo and behold we are singing; music is born; the syllable has become a note.
"ma--" just eliminate the glide; or to use our technical jargon of our time: the morpheme is re-written as a pitch event.
And what an event that must have been way back then.
What we seem to be getting to is a hypothesis that will confirm another famous cliche, namely music is hightened speech.
After all what causes such a hightening? Intensified emotions, hunger, impatience.
Certainly the deepest universals we all share are emotions, affects.
We all have the same capacity for passion, fear, anticipation, aggression.
We all display the same physiological manifestations of affect:
our eyebrows go up with anticipation; our hearts pound with passion; and fear affects us universally with gooseflesh.
And in the sense that music may express those affects being going on, then it must indeed be an universal language.
Maybe even a divine one to invoke yet another cliche. I have often thought if it's literally true that in the begining was the word,
then it must have been a sound word. The Bible tells us the whole creation story not only verbally, but in terms of verbal creation:
God said let there be light. God said let there be a firmament. He created verbally.
Can you imagine God saying just like that? "Let there be light." just as if ordering lunch;
or even in the original language, (???). I've always had a private fantacy of God singing these two blazing words.
Now that could really have done it; music could have caused light to break forth.
But all I have just done is to prolong the ictus again.
What I have created is simply hightened speech, which was seemed to corroborate yet another cliche
about music begining where language leaves off, I think Schopenhauer, that one.
In other words, if the theory of monogenesis is valid, and speech indeed have common origins;
and if the hightening of that speech produces music, then music may also be said to have common origins;
and is therefore universal whether the note issue from the Mouth of God or from that hungery infant.
But where do these  notes come from? Why do I ears select certain notes and not others.
For example, why do children tease one other in a specific sing-song way.
Two very special notes, which children also use to call one another.
Jerry, Doris, whatever!
And which are often used by them in their sing games. Little Sally Water.
That's the same two notes, only now expanded to three notes.
Little Sally Water.
Or perhaps you once yells: Ali Ali Anfery.
Does that sound familiar?
Well, again we must ask why just those notes in that particular order.
Research seems to indicate that this exact constellation of two notes and its three notes variant
is the same all over the world wherever children tease each other, on every continent and in every culture.
In short, we may have heard a clear case of a musical linguistic universal, and one in which can be identified and explained in a none-vacuous way.
I want to take a little time to do this carefully because in the explanation lies the key to musical universality in general.
The answer to that question why just those notes, and eventually to the question why those notes in Mozart,
and why those notes in Colplin, or in Schönberg, or whoever.
And in having an answer, we musicians have a singular advantage over the linguists who ask their question:
why just those sounds in human speech?
And they seek the answers by constructing a very complex hypothesis, which is still very much in the working stage,
subject to proof or disproof, amplification or derision.
But we musicians are luckier; we have the built-in, pre-ordained, universal, known as the harmonic series.
To those of you who know all about the harmonic series, I beg your indulgence for a few minutes, so that I can sketch it out for those who don't.
This accoutic phenomena, called the harmonic series or overtone series, is not hard to understand,
if you remember the basic high school fact: all sounds are produced by vibrating bodies, which send out waves.
If this vibrating body is irregularly constituted like this floor, or this piano,
it will emit waves that are irregular, and our ears will perceive them as noise
(Ou..)
But if the source of vibration is of a consistent structure, like anyone of the strings in this piano,
it will emit regular waves and we hear them as a musical tone.
Of course the source does not have to be a string, it can be a column of air as in a clarinet,
or a column of steel as in a tube of bell, or a stretched animal hide as in a kettle drum.
But whatever it is it produces what's called energy in vibratory motion, that is the official language,
by being beaten, blown, plucked, struck or frictionised with a bow.
Let's settle with a piano string, let's say this one,
which is of a particular length, tension, thickness and density.
and when struck by its hammer it produces a sound wave of a frequency of 132 vibrations per second,
and is known to the world as the note C.
Now comes the interesting part, if I sit at the piano and play that note C,
you may think you are hearing only that one tone: a dark, rich, base note.
But you are not, you are simultaneously hearing a whole series of higher tones,
but are sounding at the same time.
These are arranged in an order preordained by nature and rules by universal physical laws.
If this is news to you, I hope it's good news.
Because all these upper notes, of which maybe you are unaware,
result from a phenomenon of nature, whereby any sound producing source,
or shall I say pitch producing source such as this piano string,
vibrates not only as a whole string in all its whatever inch glory sounding that low C;
but also in fractional segments of that string, each vibrating separately.
It's as though the string were infinitely divisable into two halves,
and into three thirds and four quarters and so on.
And the smaller those segments are, the faster they vibrate,
producing higher and higher frequencies, and therefore higher and higher tones --
overtones; or harmonics, since they are sometimes called.
And these overtones or harmonics are all sounding together with the fundamental
full string. And this is basic principle  by which the entire harmonic theory is generated.
starting on any fundamental tone.
Now if you have already knew all that from high school physics,
then you'll also know that these overtones are naturally less apparent to the ear
than the fundamental, which is in this case low C.
And infact they sound more and more faintly as they go higher.
Now any note I strike will contain its own series of overtones.
But the lower the note I strike, the more abundantly audible will be its homarnic series,
which accouts in part for the comparative richness of this low C.
Now remember I spoke of the preordained order in which the overtones appear.
Let's see if I can make you actually hear those overtones in that order.
The first overtone of the series according to the laws of physics has to be
exatly an octive higher than the fundamental C we've been hearing.
In other words, this has to be this C, an octive higher.
Now if I silently press down the key of this higher C, and hold it so that the string
is free to vibrate. And then abruptly strike the fundamental C, an octive lower,
what do you hear?
You are clearly hearing the firat overtone vibrating sympathetically an octive
above its fundamental. I hope you heard it, did you? Listen again.
Clear as a bell. So obviously this upper C is an integral part of the C an octive below.
It's a built-in harmonic sounded by the two halves of that lower string vibrating independently.
Of the next overtone of this preordained order, results from that same fundamental string
vibrating in three parts; and this one will be the first different overtone, that is the
first one you will hear other than a C. That's going to be a G, this G.
Now let's repeat our experiment, I press this new one down silently, and then again
strike this fundamental C. What do we hear now? That G, right?
A new tone, again clear as a bell. You want to hear it again?
Now we've just reached a very significant point. Have you noticed that the fundamental tone
and its first overtone are really the same note C but an octive apart.
But this new overtone G is a fifth away from C.
So we now have two different tones. And once they are established in our ears, we are
in possession of the key to the whole tonal system, a system based on the concept of
tonic and dominant. Tonic and dominant. This C represents the idea of tonic, which has
the function of establishing the tonal center of any given key.
And the function of the dominant, is to aid and abet in the establishment of that tonality,
through a special relationship it enjoys with the tonic, owing to their proximity
in the harmonic series. But more of that later.
Right now onto the next overtone which is again a C, a fourth higher than the G we've just heard.
Shall we repeat the experiment? I press it down silently, there it is, you hear it?
Shall we do it again?
Now the next one is again a new pitch. This time a third higher than its predecessor.
Notice that the intervals are getting progessively smaller as we ascend the series,
began with an octive and then a fifth and then a fourth and then, now, a third.
And the new overtone will be this note E.
Listen.
It's a bit fainter, but it's there for all to hear. Shall I try it again?
Hear it way back there? One last time. It's clear.
And there you have the first four overtones of the series:
fundamental plus one two three four, three of which are of different pitches,
those three. Now it must be obvious to you that these three notes rearranged in
scale or order, constitute what is known as the major triad,
which is the very nucleus, the cornerstonec of most of the music we hear
from day to day, whether it's a symphony or a hymn, or a blues.
And this triad with its tonic-dominant relationship, plus the third sandwiched between,
this triad is the fundation of Western tonal music as it developed
of the last three centuries or so, along with the development of our western culture
in general. Let's not make the mistake so many people make
of regarding this triad as the basic universal. That's a miscomprehension that's far
too common, in that it fails to recognise that our accidental culture is only one
of many world's cultures, in spite of its current prevalence and its worldwide influence;
and in spite of the fact that it thinks it's the only important culture.
A perfect example of this, a fact of this misconception arises with the very next overtone
in the series, which is a stranger to the western tonal culture.
In fact this next overtone does not even appear on the piano, which means I cannot
demonstrate it for you as I have for the preceding ones.
More exactly stated, it is not to be found on the piano in its natural, pure form
as it derives by physical law from that fundamental C string.
Let me digress a moment to tell you why.
You see this piano, like all keyboard instruments, is a tempered instrument, which
means its notes have been tempered or "tampered with" (I don't mean a joke by that,
just mean to clarify the word).
So that each one of them, each one of these notes can serve its function in all
twelve keys at once. This readjustment in tuning became inevitable when music
reached its tonal adulthood, around 1700; and found that it didn't have to remain in
one key from the beginning to the end of a piece, but can modulate from one key
to another in the course of it; but the notes deriving naturally from
the harmonic series will work only in one key at a time. Do you follow that?
One key at a time. That is what in tune in one key is likely to be out of tune in another.
Would you believe that if this piano were to encompass only natural untempered tones, this single
octive space would have to contain 77 different keys? Well, you can understand that a compromise has
to be made somewhere, and that "somewhere" was the moment in history when the rapid development
of tonal harmony coinciding with the equally rapid development of the keyboard instruments with
their fixed, unchangeable tones. And that is how the tempered clavier chord came to be, to say
nothing of this Baldwin Grand. And that's why I can't play you this next overtone.
But if we actually approach it pianistically in our ascent of the harmonic series, we find
it somewhere around here, lieing in the crack, between this B flat and this A; it's one of those blue notes.
And that blue note can be construed by the human ear as either the higher version of the note -- B flat;
or the lower version A. In either case it requires a little push up or down to be accommodated on the piano.
But whichever way we construe it, it becomes our newest overtone.
So now we are equipped with four different overtones: the C plus the G plus the E
plus that blue note, a dubious A.
Or if we rearrange them in scaler order, C-E-G and sort of A, and here we hear a real musical linguistic
universal, because now we can understand and explain that famous worldwide teasing chat: Oly Oly Anfrey;
because all it is is a constellation of those first four different overtones,
with the tonic omitted, rather implied.
You see this tonic C, which is the same note as the fundamental C is heard in the mind's ear,
and only the three new overtones are sound. So these three universal notes are handed us by nature
on a silver platter. But why are they in this different order?
Because that's the very order in which they appear in the harmonic series. G-E and sort of A and Q-E-D.
Now this is a substantive universal, the sort of thing the linguists hunger for, but the likeness of which
are simply unavailable to them. Indeed, as we ascend further in our harmonic series,
more and more fascinating and incontrovertible universals keep appearing.
For instance this next new overtone is this one, that is the new overtone, is this one D.
So now we have five different tones to play with, which we again put into scaler order.
And pressto a new universal is given us the 5 notes or pentatonic scale.
And because of that last dubious last note, the scale can take either of two forms.
One culminating in B flat, and the other culminating in A.
Let's opt to the second of these, the lower one, which is by far the most common of the two.
This is humanity's favourite pentatonic scale, and by the way,
this is a scale you can find so easily on your own piano by playing only the black notes.
In fact, the universality of this scale is so well-known, I'm sure that you can give me examples from
all corners of the earth: from Scotland -- pure pentatonic; or from China; or from Africa
and from the American-Indian cultures, and from Eastern Indian cultures
and from central and south Amerima, and Australia and Finland.
Well, that's a true musical linguistic universal.
But let's be careful about making linguistic analogies.
We could conceivably equate a fundamental tone, such as this C, with the basic morpheme "ma",
which we discovered before; and then extend the parallel equating the overtones of that
fundamental C with a set of words evolving from that "ma" syllable.
Maybe! It's all still speculation. But what appears to be much more convincing is the analogy
between Chomtsky's innate grammatical competence and the innate musical grammatical competence,
which we may all possess universally; that is our in-built capacity to construe those naturally
serialised overtones and to contrue them in different ways.
Just as the various cultures of the world may have construed basic monogenetic materials and
constructed out of them thousands of particular grammars or languages, all different from one another.
Analagously, varied human cultures can construe this pentatonic scale in different ways,
depending for example on which of the five notes is taken to be the tonal center.
For example this one: that's one way.
Or this one: you see how it makes the whole different pentatonic but the same five notes.
Or this one, same five notes again but a different scale.
And there is always that blue notes to be considered.
If the ear construes it as the upper B flat instead of the lower A, it will give us a whole
other pentatonic scale, which produces some beautiful African music.
And there are even much more complix processes which we won't go into, but which account for
the existence of the  highly differentiated Japanese pentatonic scale. Does that sound familiar?
Or the unique pentatonic scale of the Balinese music.
But enough of pentatonics. I think we have seen enough of the way the harmonic series uprates,
to recognise the fact that as we ascend the series, always find new tones to be added (Oops..).
There we are, to be added to our collection, we can eventually account for six and seven notes
scales including Greek modes and church modes, and the diatonic scales both major and minor,
and eventually all twelve tones of our so-called chromatic scale; which is of course due to
the merit of tempering. We get those equidistant tones.
And you may well ask why just twelve tones. Patience, you'll find out in a minute.
But even these twelve tones don't exauhst the potential of the harmonic series;
the upper reaches of the seires contintue to furnish us with intervals even smaller than the
half tones that make up our chromatic scale.
Intervals that such as quarter tones, or even thirds and fifths of tones, all of which are still
inhabit the areas of experimentation, like electronic research; to say nothing of microtones,
which are such an essential part of so much oriental music.
But the overrating fact that emerges from all this is that all music, whether pop, folk, symphonic
modal, tonal, atonal, poly-tonal, micro-tonal, well-tempered or ill-tempered, music from the
distant past or the imminent future, all of it has a common origin in the universal phenomenon
of the harmonic serials. And that is our case for musical monogenesis.
But is it a case necessarily for music universality? Think!
What about those Hindu Ragas so many people find difficult to comprehend.
Well I suggest a simple answer. In the light of our linguistic analogies, just as the
grammars of the human languages, even mutually unintelligible ones, may have sprung from the
same monogenetic sources, so in the same way, highly varied musical tongues, which are also
strangers to one another, can be said to have developed out of their common origins.
In purely phonological terms, these tongues are tonal languages that have developed out of a
universal, naturally ordered, tonal structure.
Now I trust you realise that all of this has been enormously compressed and undocumented by
historical musical examples, because that's gonna take all night;
but this is not a linguistic course; nor is it a history of music course.
What we are trying for is a very high overview of musical development in terms of a vocabulary
constantly being enriched, by more and more remote and chromatic overtones.
It's as if we can see the whole of music developing from prehistory to the present in two minutes.
Let's again pretend that we're homonids, and the smash hit moment is, let's say Fair Harvard.
Here we are, in our homonid hut crooning, and now maybe our wives and maybe our pre-pubescence sons join in,
automatically, we are singing not in unison, but in octives, since men's and women's voices
are naturally an octive apart. Now that octive interval,
I wish I could sing an octive so I can really show you what I mean. But that octive interval
happens to be the first interval of the harmonic series as you remember, right?
OK. Now centuries passed and the next interval of the harmonic series is assimilated by humanity,
namely the fifth. And now we can be singing this.
Now of course this little change brings us forward a mere ten million years,
into the tenth century AD, an interval of fairly sophisticated musical culture.
But now we admit the next interval of the series, the fourth; and now we can mix intervals
of the ocitive and the fifth and the fourth.
Now that's beginning to sound like polyphony.
And again comes a great leap, as music absorbs the next overtone, the third.
And just listen to the difference.
It's a whole new music, richer, melodier, with a new colouristic warmth.
And as we know, this new interval of the third, bacause I like the older sound better,
anyway, ah...
As we know the new interval of the third introduces into music the phenomenon of the triad,
so that now Fair Harvard can begin to sound more like its Victorian self.
And so there was born, what we now call, tonal music; a stable tonal language,
firmly rooted in the basic notes of the harmonic series:
The fundamental and its first different overtone, the fifth; now and for evermore to be known
as the tonic and the dominant. And that fifth interval really does dominate,
because once this tonic-dominant relationship is established, it's a feel???? day for composers.
There can be now a fifth of fifth of fifth of fifth;
each one of them, a new tonic producing a new dominant, a whole circle of fifths;
twelve of them in fact; always winding up with the starting tone;
whether proceeding upwards, let's say
from the low C, G, D, A, E, B, F#, C#, G#, Eb, Bb, F, C.
That's again C,  believe or not that?
Or proceeding downwards, starting from that
C, F, Bb, Eb, Ab, Db, Gb, B, E, A, D, G, C
back to C, that's the circle of twelve fifths, and that's the answer I promised you;
that's how we got our twelve different tones of our chromatic scale.
Because if you take all those twelve of the circle of fifths, and put them together
in scale order, you'll get this.
And what's more those twelve notes generate a circle of twelve different keys,
through which, thanks to the perfecting of the tempered system, composers can now
go free willing at their own chromatic pleasure.
And this means ultimately Fear Harvard can sound like this.
That's chromatic porrige; and in our own century it's going to become goulash.
How does music contain this loose runny chromaticism?
By the basic principle of diatonicism; that stable relationship
of tonics, dominants, sub-dominants, and super-tonics and new dominants and
new tonics, and now we modulate as freely as we want, as chromatically as we want,
and stil have complete tonal control.
This great system of tonal controls was perfected and codified by Bach, J.S.Bach,
whose genius was to balance so delicately and so justly these two forces of
chromaticism and diatonicism, forces that are equally powerful and presumably
contradictory in nature.
And this point of delicate balance is like the still center in the stormy flux of
musical history.
A condition of such stability that was able to continue with out remarkable changes
for almost a century; and this roughly a hundred years became a golden age.
This is not to say that the world drastic changes in style and form in those a hundrend years.
It's after all this golden age saw emergence of a whole new Rococo style; to say nothing
of the phenomenal rise of sonata form and the hands of such giants as C.P.E.Bach and Haydn and Mozart and
Beethoven himself.
But these changes are syntactic and semantic changes, which will be examining and enjoying in future lectures.
Right now, we are limiting our investigation to phonology;
and in these terms, we can see the peak attained by Bach,
continuing as s kind of a plateau, level and lofty right in to the music of Beethoven.
Now at this point, I'd like to invite you to listen with me to one of the supreme examples of this golden age:
Mozart's G minor symphony, a work of utmost passion utterly controlled
and of free chromaticism elegantly contained.
I'll try to prepare you a bit somewhat with a few illustrations of this control and containment,
so that you can hear the symphony, hopefully with fresh phonological ears.
Remember what we are looking for is the wonderfully creative way in which chromatic flexibility
can be systematically contained within the framework of tonic-dominant relationships.
It's a curious thing and a crucial one, that through this perfect combination of opposites,
chromaticism and diatonicism, there is distiled the essence of ambiguity of all things.
This word "ambiguity" may seem to be the most unlikely word to use to speak of a golden age
composers like Mozart, a master of clarity and precision.
But ambiguity has always inhabited musical art, indeed all the arts; because it's one of art's most
potent aesthetic functions.
More ambiguous, more expressive, up to a certain point.
Of course there is a limit, which we are going to run into in the course of these lectures.
We are going to run into a state of such increased ambiguity
that problems of musical clarity are bound to arise; and that's where we'll be confronted head on
by Ive's unanswered question: whither. Meanwhile, we are still in the golden age with ambiguity
classically contained in the Augusten balances and proportions in here into this Moart's symphony.
Let's look at it very briefly.